software engineer radio episode 88 the
singularity research OS with Galen
Hunter this is software engineering
radio the podcast for professional
developers on the web at s e - radio
dotnet se radio prints irrelevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
soft engineering topics every 10 days
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our web site for supporting
the hot rod
[Music]
hello this is another episode of
software engineering radio please take a
look at se - radio net and specifically
at the link that leads you to the SE
radio get together our 2008 open space
meeting it'll happen
notify Putin Germany October 16th and
17th its co-organized with deep boomed
Falak yeah well we would like to see you
there
please go to the website look at the PDF
and consider coming another thing I want
to briefly talk about only in this
episode is that we'll have a little buff
birds of feathers sessions in AQ Khan in
London Q Khan is actually in next week
from March 10 - what is it 14 or
something and on the Thursday evening
between 7:30 and 8:30 p.m. we'll have a
little well we just meet and talk a
little bit about SU radio give us
feedback and on some additional episodes
and just you know talk a little bit
about things if you're a Q Khan you're
obviously invited to join thanks Miguel
who know for actually organizing this
so maybe see you there Thursday 7:30 to
8:30 in room 1 whatever that is I guess
we'll find out once we're at Q Khan okay
let's get ahead with the actual episode
this is an episode that's somewhat
special because first of all it's a
research topic we are talking about and
the other thing is that I'm actually at
Microsoft Research the first time I've
ever been there so the episode is about
the singularity operating system
research project and we're talking two
gallon hunt so welcome Galan to the show
oh thank you very much Marcus so why
don't you introduce yourself a little
bit to our listeners
so I'm Galen hunt I run the operating
systems research group here Microsoft
Research in Redmond I've been at
Microsoft Research about ten years
before that I was at the University of
Rochester where I did my graduate degree
and my primary interest is around
operating systems but I've done some
distributed systems that do other things
I spend
most of my 10 years here in research but
I did spend four years of my time
Microsoft in the windows about no two
and a half years sorry in the Windows
Server division okay can you give us one
minute overview what is singularity in a
nutshell and maybe how is it different
from traditional operating systems such
as Windows so in a nutshell singularity
is a brand new operating system it's a
research prototype that we've built from
scratch in using managed languages so
c-sharp in particular c-sharp and and
other languages singularity is a
microkernel type architecture so it's
very similar in that way but the key
idea is to see if we could build an
entire operating system out of safe code
from the ground up and to see how
aggressively we could use tools and
language and and operating system
architecture innovations to allow us to
build a system that the fundamentally we
could check for errors before we ever
shipped the code rather than try the
test amount so that the problem you want
to solve is is stability reliability
dependability or mode you phrased the
way I describe it is dependability and
the simple way I describe it is how do
you make a system that has predictable
behavior because if you think about what
users want one mean when they say
dependable they mean I know what it's
gonna do and I know how it's gonna react
in and it's gonna be meet my
expectations mmm-hmm maybe before we go
to the to the solution approach and the
patterns and the stuff you did why why I
mean why our traditional operating
systems not dependable what what's the
problem is it just history it just
became like that or are there any new
key technologies that make operating
systems potentially dependable these
days well I think if you if you look at
the what I'll call commodity operating
systems Windows Linux the the systems
that we use vary widely if you think
about them they're really were designed
on architectures from the early 1970s ok
30 year old languages 30 old operating
system technologies and it was a very
different world than we live in right
now it was a world in which for example
you either in the 1970s if you had a
computer you either weren't connected to
a network of any
and never seen a network or you were
connected to a network that everybody
else on the network was funded by the
same funding agency okay
whereas now you're connected the
Internet with lots of people that not
only aren't paid by the same funding and
an agency but some of them would like to
separate you from your funding agency
for example of your funds right a very
hostile world another place where I
think things have changed very radically
over the last thirty years is it 30
years ago if you were using a computer
and using an operating system you were
probably a a graduate student or at
least a computer science or something
like that right and whereas now we have
you know so then you really wanted to
know about computers and now if you most
people use a computer they don't have
any clue how a computer works they don't
want to know how a computer works they
just want it to work for them so our
assertion is that hey if the world has
changed that dratted radically well then
maybe the systems that we're using well
they're obviously don't fit very well
right and we see this with all sorts of
security problems and bugs and other
things and and so that said well let's
start over from scratch thinking about
what would a computer system look like
it was designed for the modern world in
its context ok so let's look at the
solution at the architectural
foundations of the solution can you give
us an overview of what these are so
singularity as I mentioned I want
probably the most important things is it
is written in safe code from the ground
up so there's a whole class of errors
that exist in current systems buffer
overruns things like that that don't
exist in this system there because you
know they've been they've been by design
not allowed in the system
singularity itself as I already
mentioned it's kind of it's a
microkernel type architecture so there's
a closed kernel at the bottom that's
sealed off and then all of the code runs
above the kernel in processes and
singularity supports three kind of
primary abstractions I guess I would
call them so there's three core ideas in
the architecture the first one is what
we call a software isolated process the
second one is that the communication
between processes is through channel
based contracts so
with rich information and the third one
is an idea that we call manifest based
programs mm-hmm so if I were a buzz word
person then I would say this sounds like
us away but I don't want to do
everything but there is clearly
something which people often call as
component based software development
where is what we're a component has a
well-defined dependence or well-defined
dependencies on its environment and so
it's not a surprise if you run a
component what it wants from its
environments formally specified so it it
clearly isn't that tradition right yeah
you know traditionally when you talk
about component a good way I would
describe it is you have you have a piece
of software and it has some dependencies
and those dependencies are expressed in
a way that a human can understand them
that's the traditional way that's the
traditional yeah
right and in singularity where this idea
of a manifest based program and also the
channel contracts yeah what we've
actually done is specified the
requirements in such a way that a
computer can process them and not just
in the source code but in the final
binary yeah we we have this idea a term
that I use which is a self describing
artifact mmm idea is that I'd be able to
pick up a piece of software the binary
they'll get it and know exactly what its
requirements are to run and how it
interacts with the rest of the world so
if you specify what this is what this
thing is and what it expects from the
rest of the world how far down do you go
there I mean obviously one thing is easy
you can say I want to communicate to
this other thing which maybe has a type
so that's relatively easy to specify and
then you have this concept of channel so
I guess your components say I want to
talk to this channel but do you also
formally specify something about the
real behavior of the thing we so we
aren't doing formal specifications so
the way I would answer that is we we
describe how you interact yeah so what
my boss so so like what your yeah so
it's kind of a black box but the channel
contracts describe your behavior as
another party would see it through this
particular communication interface but
within you we don't describe what
happens inside your insight you know
okay a good way I describe is
we'll say what we know what you're gonna
say and what are the ways that you can
put language together there but we're
not gonna tell you how you're gonna
think yeah and what this means yes yeah
so that the contract-based channels
basically means that you specify message
interactions what goes in what goes out
how you react to a specific message yes
so we specified the the contracts
specified the messages are allowed to go
across a channel of this particular type
and it also has a state machine that
describes the patterns of the of the
communication so a good example this is
you know most people would recognize
pretty easily as when I open when I
access a file in traditional operating
system I'll open the file the operating
system will say okay it's open and then
I can have them adieu my read and write
requests and then when I'm done I can
say closed and you know there's an
implied state machine of I can't have
reads and writes before I do an open or
after a closed yeah and so this is just
a for kind of a formal mechanism that
you can express those types of
relationships and it lets us do some
very powerful so we can actually compile
these contracts we can also take the
binary for a program that implements a
contract you know say a client for
example and we can analyze the code oh
cool and we can detect if the client
actually conforms to the contract so you
don't do it with a runtime watchdog that
starts shouting if you don't comply to
the contract but rather you can do this
statically yes and so we can actually
check it on the developer's desktop so I
have a for me a very fun story around
this which is we got the key channel
mechanism up and running and had
singularities running web server
benchmarks for about a year before we
had the verifier online and when we got
the verifier online we loaded in the
contract for TCP sockets and talking for
the two with the tcp/ip stack and we ran
it across the the channel contract and
we found there was an error in the
contract so we fixed the contract and
then we ran it across the server code
and our web server and it turned out we
had a case where we weren't handling
what happens if you went if the web
server went to the socket ask for data
and there was no data available and it
didn't correctly handle handle this case
so it was a what we'd call a Heisenberg
so she's a bug had been in the code for
literally a year yeah
and we we had never diagnosed it never
probably never even realized it was
there just had server runs that didn't
run every well yeah we ran this verifier
and literally within like two minutes of
when we started the verifier on the code
we had the verifier came up and said you
have an error in this line of code and
you aren't handling the case when
there's no data mmm cool because the
state machine basically had a state or a
transition that wasn't followed there
was a trend there was this message there
in this state that we saw there was
three messages here's the data the other
end is closer to channel or there's no
data and we weren't handling no no yeah
and this was the day that the engineers
on the project up until then they had
complained very vocally about these
contracts that they were on the way
there were a lot of work yeah and the
day that we found one of these bugs was
a very subtle bug the engineers stopped
complaining from then on there been very
gung-ho about that it's interesting
we've had an episode a while ago on
static analysis tools and actually I
forget who we did this with anyway the
guy basically explained that building
these tools is quite complex because you
have to understand what the code does
now I assume because you have the
contracts formally specified in the
state machine so you do a lot of these
things declaratively so in analysis is
probably relatively easy because it's
clear how the communication happens it's
not just a side effect of something yes
in fact this was one of the one of the
key insights in the team if you look at
the composition of the singularity team
you'll find that a large portion of the
number of people involved in the project
our static analysis team Alerus is
software improvement group so these guys
that are world experts on static
analysis yeah and one of the insights of
singularity who said we're gonna create
the operating system with the intent
that we can do as much as static
analysis at all at all so we we have
contracts that are easier to verify you
know not only do we have the world's
best static an analysis in researchers
who also make their life easier we've
also yeah that's a we've done a good way
to say we've done everything we could to
meet them in the middle the halfway
ground yeah and it's actually something
I've talked about a lot I work a lot in
modern software development and
cogeneration and I always say the more I
can do declaratively as opposed to
having it in a as a protocol somewhere
in the code the better
because all the stuff that's burned in
the code is gone absolutely okay so that
was a long penchant anyway let's let's
look briefly about the software isolated
processes I mean it to me it sounds well
I know that's probably not the case but
you could argue that sounds like
overhead and sounds like it's slow
because there is all the stuff in
managed languages and in mind the
switching context overhead might be
worse compared to native low-level stuff
so do you have any any any comparison
with regards to performance in fact it's
faster okay so the key thing so so let
me let me drill in explain the software
isolated process more so in a
traditional operating system you think
of a process as a set of pages and then
the our operating system uses hardware
protection mechanisms to keep you from
using a pointer to touch another
processes memory when it's software
isolated process what we do is we
instead we take the code the code has to
be written in a safe language and we
verify that it is statically that it is
incapable of generating a pointer to
someone else's memory and so then we can
run the processes without any hardware
protection at all replacing the hardware
protection with static verification so
we actually have a research paper that's
on the website where we did a detail
analysis of what the cost of hardware is
and guess what this hardware protection
that you always thought was free in fact
isn't free it costs you depending on the
scenario and how you're using it
anywhere from 3 to 38 percent of your
performance it's used up in fact you
know minimal case just turning on the
TLB the translation lookaside mechanism
from physical to virtual virtual to
physical addresses cost you on the order
about 3 percent of your performance ok
and so we are able to get rid of all
those the overhead of the hardware
we're also when you say talk about a
context switch we don't have to change
address basis and reprogram the hardware
when we change context and so actually
our context switches are between 5 and
10 times faster than traditional
operating systems cool the last thing we
didn't talk about explicitly is the
manifest best manifest best program
again the key idea with these manifest
based programs is getting back this idea
of a self
describing artifact yeah and and being
able to analyze not only individual
programs but the entire operating system
so even the kernel in our case has a
manifest cool and what this has allows
us to do is we can take the entire
system and when you come and try to
install a new program we can tell you at
install time if it's gonna break
compatibility or interact in a bad way
with any other part of this version I
guess so there's a notion of very very
rich versions yeah and we also have very
rich dependency information so you can
ask you can literally ask a question
before you ever run the code you can say
is this program capable of running
correctly on my hardware and software
configuration so something we should
probably tell our listeners is that
there is a really nice paper you wrote
and that's what I read somewhere on the
web and that's the basis for this
interview so I read about the Singh
sharp language so what language support
do you have probably it's built on top
of c-sharp I guess so what's in addition
to c-sharp in that language so there's
actually three languages involved here
ok so sing sharp is built on top of a
language called spec sharp came out of
Wolfram Schultz group here desert which
is built on top of c-sharp
okay so spec sharp adds pre and post
condition right around 4 I read that
somewhere and invariance you can put an
object invariance and then what seems
sharp adds to spec sharp on top of that
his first class mechanisms were talking
about communication so sending and
receiving messages and operations around
communication or first class operations
there's also support for what we call
linear types so in in singularity when
you communicate there's no shared memory
between processes you communicate by
exchanging Metro and there's a mechanism
that we can we can use it's called a
linear type and what that means is these
as well I'll describe it is only one
person can hold a pointer to a
participant I'm and so when you give the
memory off to someone else we can
actually look at your code and know that
you're never going to try to access that
memory again so it it it makes it makes
it so we can do very cheap communication
so that's the point because if you do
message passing in traditional systems
you physically have to copy the stuff
and that's big overhead and what you do
is you you
avoid that you've basically exchanged a
pointer but you are sure that nobody can
mess around once you hand it off that's
right and so it allows the communication
to be extremely cheap there and also
statically verify it right and because
it's all in one big process because you
isolate via software and not by a
machine process things you actually can
share the memory yes reminds me a little
bit of of Erlang the the Erlang language
there is there are some similarities I
recently talked to Joe Armstrong about
it so what's the the process you work
you've probably first described your
contracts and then you I would guess
generate some kind of Stella Excalibur
gainst which you then implement the
component or how does this work well so
you specify your contracts first and and
you you you write them in sets the other
things were seen Sharpe has is the
contract language is actually sing
Sharpe yeah so you write it you know
just like you're writing strux or
something here's my set of messages
here's the here's the channel contract
and then from a piece of code you Union
your c-sharp code you import that
namespace contract and then you can just
use it okay and program again okay
because it's all based on the CLR and so
there's no code generation involved
there that's right what is the role of
the kernel actually we in an se radio we
didn't have an episode on operating
systems yet maybe I'm sure
so can you briefly explain what the
kernel does and what it how it's
different from traditional kernels if
there is a difference okay well so in a
traditional kernel traditional operating
system like Windows or say Linux the
kernel does everything okay the colonel
had knows how to talk to the disk the
maternal has a file system the kernel
has a network stack for sending messages
the kernel hosts all of the device
drivers and then the kernel does basic
things like providing access to memory
scheduling threads managing resources
and things like that singularity is what
we call a microkernel design and it's an
it's an old the idea of a microkernel is
pretty old it dates back to the well
relatively old abates back dates back to
the 80s with mock and and some other
systems your your European you listeners
should recognize l4 for example is one
of the key micro kernels okay anyway if
they know operating systems singularity
and so what this means for singularity
is that the kernel and singularity
provides some very basic
services it provides the ability to
create processes and shut them down the
ability to create threads of execution
within processes the ability to for
processes to access to acquire in
release memory when they need it and it
also contains ability to send and
receive messages to to other process it
dispatches them or is it like just
another component which others can talk
to the abstraction we present is of the
channel entry point and then the kernel
mechanism is you can send a message on
an endpoint and it does the kernel
manages that the transfer of that
message like an orb in some sense yeah
to to the other to the other process and
then you know you can receive a message
which is to take the message off of the
outer channel yeah ok and it's visit
that portion is actually very very
lightweight but so it's it's a fairly
minimal kernel and then all of the
services that you particularly think of
operating services so the network stack
the filesystem the device drivers run as
separate processes of sips these
software isolated processes up above the
kernel um when one of the key benefits
of that for singularity is if you think
about a traditional system like say
Windows device drivers run in the kernel
space and so if you know they're just
bits
yeah mung the rest of the kernel bits
yeah and so if a device driver fails the
whole kernel goes the blue screen of
death right yeah well one of the things
you find is that device drivers are much
more prone to failure then say kernel
code okay
in singularity well these device drivers
run in separate sips and so if a device
driver fails we can just close it and
start up another one for example yeah
so the you mentioned it before that the
kernel is written in C sharp or Singh
sharp not in C or assembly language or
or stare a little well so yes so the way
I describe is the primary language we've
implemented is C sharp or well okay so I
always say C sharp it's actually Singh
sure plus your yeah plus C plus these
contract settings and the way to say it
is 95% of
by the line count 95% of the kernel is
written in c-sharp and then we still
have assembly code basically the same
place you know if you looked at say the
Linux source code you'd see that most of
it's written in C but there's places
where there's assembly so like the
context switch code for thread context
switch interrupt vectors at the bottom
and things like that are still assembly
yeah
another abbreviation that sounded to be
quite central as ABI ah what's that you
know avi is that's funny when everybody
always fast me what does ABI mean it's
actually a very old term particularly
from the UNIX world and it means an
application binary interface and what it
means is it's it's a very formal
description of the interface between a
program and the kernel okay
so typically in in in historical UNIX
context it means you know what are what
is the binary format of a program what
is the syscall interface between the
program and the kernel that's at cetera
and in singular we have likewise have a
very concrete kind of formal description
of what the interface is between a
program and the kernel so what are the
services that a program receives from
the kernel it sounds to me like channels
or endpoints this it's a very good
question here's the simple way I can
answer that question because some in
fact in some of our academic papers some
of the comments that come back is well
why aren't you using channels for
everything why is it that's currently
yeah yep here's a simple reason if I
send a message on a channel there has to
be some way for me to tell the colonel
okay send this message on this channel
okay so there's some basic primitive
operations and and receipt yeah those
are exposed as a be eyes see you
actually we have there's more than just
that and there's a I think it's very one
at one of the very unique aspects of the
singularity design is that the ABI the
way I would think describe it is it
gives a program a guaranteed subset of
functionality around pure computation I
can create threads
I can run threads I can synchronize
threads I can get memory
I can communicate with other process
through sips and that that set of
functionality is always available to any
program regardless of which version of
singularity it's running on or what
other services might be there it also
means that you can always count it and
count on it and it also one of the
things that lets us do very very easily
is sandboxing ok so Windows for example
or Linux has a very hard time with how
do I run a piece of code like it'll you
know some random code that I bring off
the internet that I want to be able to
say computation but I want to know it's
not going to go talk to my file system
or send spam or anything like that
well that ABI lets you give a base
abstraction for everything you need for
a language runtime to run and then we
give you channels for the additional
things that we want you to do so if we
want you to be able to draw the screen
we'll give you a channel to the screen
if we want you to be able to talk the
filesystem we'll give you a channel to a
file system or a subset of it and the
important one of the important works you
mentioned was give you so you cannot
just grab channel you have to declare it
probably somewhere and then you're given
the channel and the giver decides
whether this is maybe just a mark or
whether it's the real thing and yes I'm
an exactly the case and so the giver can
decide and so and and it does have to be
declared in your manifest and not only
does it have to be declared in your
manifest but we also take your binary
and we'll analyze it you know at install
time and make sure that you aren't
hiding in some place in your code that
you're going to try to talk to say the
tcp/ip stack and spam yeah so there's
this other thing called capabilities
that I have to kind of make sense of in
that context is that's something we
already covered or the short answer is
that channels are capabilities okay if I
give you a channel endpoint
I'm giving you the capability to
communicate with somebody okay and so
this allows us to use singularity as a
capability type system where you know
where I can talk about a program has
these capabilities because I've given
out this endpoints okay one last
question about this chorus stuff you
mentioned that sips have threats now sip
sound to me relatively lightweight why
do you need threats why don't not have
one and have just hundreds of thousands
or whatever of
of sips of processes that's a good
question so actually our threads are
even lighter weight than traditional
threads they don't have to they have a
mechanism we call link stacks for
example so they're very very lightweight
they're even lighter weight than sips
the answers that is well we think that
there's quite often the case that people
take in order to express parallelism
that they need shared memory yep and so
and and since we don't allow shared
memory between sips the only way to do
that is inside a given sip with threads
so the argument that they have shared
memory and therefore our faster than
processes doesn't really count because
you have shared memory at least on the
exchange heap between processes yeah
except for I'll be very clear with this
when we say so the exchange heap is not
shared across top of a well from a
performance perspective it's shared I'm
a programming model is different that's
right from the performance perspective
it's like shared memory yeah from the
correctness perspective yes we always
guarantee that only one sip owns can
access that memory at any given time
yeah very nice okay so this was kind of
the core of the system and you mentioned
obviously before that this is still a
research system so you also do
explorative exploratory well you do
experiments based on that party and so
can we look a little bit about what some
of these experiments are one one thing
you've mentioned your paper is compile
time reflection yes so that that's what
was one of my favorite experiments so
one of the things that we say in
singularity is that the processors are
sealed okay so this means when we start
up a process you have before you start
the process you have to name all the
code that's going to run in that process
and once you begin execution you can't
alter the codes inside that you can't
add new code for example and we also the
other thing we do is we I think I
mentioned already is we can even though
we write the code in c-sharp
we're not a JIT a just-in-time
environment like the JVM like the CLR
we're actually comply ahead of time
compiled environment ok so it installed
time when you install a program we take
the MSI l the intermediate
language from the CLR that the c-sharp
programs are compiled into we take that
MSI L and we compile it into the native
instruction set that processors process
our processors on your machine yeah and
so this makes traditional dynamic
reflection fairly difficult and so we
came up with this alternative mechanism
we called compile time reflection and
basically the idea is if you look at the
way people use a reflection
almost like 90 percent of the uses a
reflection or for marshaling and inter
process communication and serialization
and things like that and that stuff
doesn't really need to be dynamic sure
you know the develop the weight think
about is a human has expressed their
intent before that code runs yeah and so
what we've done is we with we've given a
mechanism called compile time reflection
where the programmer can say hey for
example if I'm generating marshaling
code here's what the marshalling
templates look like and then we actually
add when we compile we go and generate
all the code instead of doing it so for
that to do that the same Sharpe language
has this transform primitive or the
standard form things yes that's right
and basically you build some templates
and you say here here's you have a
matching template so this is you know
whenever you see a pattern that looks
like say a class that has this
serialized attribute now then you have a
template say then generate this body of
code so it typically looks like if you
find a class has a serialized attribute
generate the right to string method and
here's what the body should look and
because it's compiled time the nice
thing is that in if in subsequent code
you actually call this automatically
generated method from compiler will not
complain because the at that time the
method is actually really there that's
right the method is really there and
it's also much faster yes if you do it
dynamically um I did some experience I
don't I actually do not remember if we
ever published this result but I can I
actually did an implementation on the
seal our communication between two app
domains and the CLR yeah one using the C
large building remoting and the other
one using compile time reflection
compile time reflection one is 50 times
fast yeah I believe that we actually had
an episode a while ago with a Lauren
strat about his converge language which
also sabab compile time
our programming compile-time macros so
that ties in actually it's a very active
area absolutely so you already said that
there is this possibility of adding an
attribute to something and then
automatically transforming that into
code so that's probably so the question
is how is this meta programming thing
used in the platform how do the manifest
based things how does that you know go
together so one of the one of the in
fact the very first place that we
applied it in fact kind of the
motivating scenario for doing the
compile time reflection was for the
device drivers so if you think about a
device driver if I'm a video device
driver I have a set of resources that I
want from the hardware I want access to
the i/o ports for that device that I'm
the driver for I want access to the
memory buffers and other things like
that and traditionally the way this is
done is when you your device driver
starts up it goes off and it ask for
these resources and interacts with the
with the operating system dynamically
that's for the resources yeah and
there's as a side effect if you pick up
the code for a device driver the binary
in a traditional operating system you
can't say anything about you have no
idea what the dependencies are okay
well it's singularity what we do is we
actually put in there's an object that
you build into your device driver that
has a set of attributes and you label
explicitly what are the resources you
want as objects with labels and then and
then you just use that object you never
ask for your resources okay as you
express your code you just use it and
then what happens is well we we read
your binary we create the manifest for
your binary and when and then we use the
compile time reflection to generate all
the code that knows how to given the
some operations from the kernel I use
access to those resources him and so we
can check all your dependencies but we
can also we give you this added benefit
of well we generate this code for you
automatically sounds a bit like
dependency injection in some sense I
mean you specify what you want
explicitly formally machinery doubly and
then you have some external power which
reads the stuff and gives you what you
need it's exactly what happens yeah yeah
very nice I mean I have two little
tangent here I mean I've been talking
about this
driven component-based development for
ages specifying in models what a
component does and all this stuff so to
me what you do here is is really taking
this to the to the right level making
this the operating system paradigm as
opposed to having that somewhere in a
system so to me this is really
absolutely cool I really like it we're
trying to be cool I'm not sure that it's
necessarily cool to the general public I
mean it's not a hype topic it's so up
it's it's hard to explain it to my wife
okay so and and one of the nice things
of compile-time metaprogramming as
opposed to runtime is of course also
that your static analysis tools and your
dependability analyses work on the
result of the metaprogramming
transformation steps
that's right can't cheat yeah and in
fact the templates are specified in such
a way we can specify we can we can
statically check the template and know
that it will only ever generate valid
code we're safe use dynamic reflection
it's a very low-level interface you can
you there's no way to tell ahead of time
that the code will be correct yeah okay
let's look at another experiment and
everybody knows that the world is going
to be radically different in a couple of
years because we all have 55 thousand
different course on the processors so
this whole thing of multi processing SMP
multi-core is probably something you
couldn't have ignored when building
singularity no we kind of ignored it and
we fact we found a few opportunities so
the base singularity system is is multi
multi-threaded multi-core so we you know
give it 16 processors and it's just
happy to chunk away and use all of them
but we've also done some experiments
around this idea of that we call
heterogeneous multi-core so if you look
at you know if you have 55,000
processors on your machine just you're
just to pick around a number we don't
think they're all gonna look the exact
same okay there's lots of reasons for
power consumption or resource
utilization do you want to actually have
different sets of course if you've got
that much hardware and so one of the
things we've been looking at is how do
we make a programming model that lets
you express your program and run it and
if you have you know 15 different core
types of core
in there that we can use them you know a
good example is we can you let you build
a program that's able to use your GPU
and your CPU and say a special processor
on your i/o cards simultaneously and you
don't have to worry about well how do I
program a GPU just write the code and we
managed to generate the right code to
run on the scene on the GPU for you the
other thing that we've done in this
experiment is an idea that we call of
subservient kernel
so you find if you look at these many
core systems so if you have 55,000 cores
pick a random number they're not all
going to have the same size cache we
have on current machines the hashes tend
to be smaller and so that means the
amount of code you want to run on that
particular court you want it to be
smaller okay
and so decide so we came across this
idea of well you know a lot of these
cores don't need to actually run very
much the operating system in fact they
might want to run just a very very small
center of the operating system and this
thing we call the subservient kernel and
and we can scale it everywhere from it's
a pure kernel that runs side by side
with the other kernel just on separate
cores or down to a very small kernel
that's about 12 K in size that doesn't
do anything other than forward request
to a master kernel on another processor
the other thing I read about was
hardware protection domains so although
we discussed or you mentioned that that
you do everything software isolated Lee
there are still some hardware thing in
there so why and and what does it do
well so one of the questions we got
asked when we were going around and
giving the academic cop talks on
singularity is you know it's hardware
protection really that expensive or what
if I run out of address space because
you're sharing it with all the processes
so we added this idea of a hardware
protection domain and it is a hardware
based protection Amane it's an address
space okay so the way you could think of
it is almost our traditional you know
heavyweight Hardware type process and we
can we can generate them as a runtime
decision you could say oh I want to take
this zip or this set of five sips and
place them into our Hardware protection
domain so for example if you have a sip
that came from the outside world you
know from you know
hostile entity you're not sure what it's
really going to do but you really need
to run it you can put it in one of these
harder protection campaigns and get an
extra level of protection or another
example is a piece of code like sequel
server wants to have lots of virtual
memory and so you can give it its own
virtual address space and so we can have
hardware protection domains our separate
address spaces and they can be either
privileged so they run it the same
protection level as the kernel or as
user mode so we can so you can either
look at it as belts and suspenders or a
way to be able to expose more rich
capabilities out of the hardware but not
have to you the key thing is you can use
it when you want it but if you don't
need it you don't have pretty for the
class now you also have a typed assembly
language which to me almost sounds like
an oxymoron so so type to assembly
languages about this we have so remember
we're saying we're relying on static
verification to provide protection so so
we take MSI l code and we converted to
x86 code and in in singularity in the
Ridgid as originally conceived without
type of assembly language what that
means is essentially the compiler is
part of the trusted computing base so if
the compiler messes up and lets the
programmer do you know manipulate memory
incorrectly
the security whole systems grow well
been compromised what typed assembly
language what you do is the compiler in
addition to emitting the assembly code
you know the Machine operations also
emits a proof that the code that it's
generated is typed safe and then when
you load in that binary there's a very
small checker it's you know it's on the
order of a thousand few thousand lines
of code that checks the bind the typed
assembly language to make sure that it
is in fact type safe and that allows you
to take the compiler out of the trusted
computing base so anybody can build a
compiler they can build a compiler for
whatever instruction set or they want
but we can still verify and still have
safety assuming that other compiler also
outputs this metadata that answers for
proving things yes yep
okay so we're coming up to the towards
the end slowly but certainly so let's
let's think about a couple of concluding
thoughts we already talked about the
performance of this thing a little bit
it was interesting thing with the
performance when we designed the system
and when we were originally planning it
we said you know dependability is far
more important than performance
absolutely you know that I think there
are people they would would be happy to
have a computer that was 20% slower if
they knew that if they were never gonna
get another virus right it's better Lee
since next year it's gonna be as fast as
now yeah exactly and so so we set off
saying you know we're not gonna care
about performance it needs to be fast
enough that people will use it but it
doesn't need to be the fastest operating
system on the planet and we were very
surprised when we got the full thing up
and running that in fact it's got very
good performance because of the software
isolation for example so so this
dependability actually buys us some
performance in some cases so it's a
pleasant surprise but not you know even
if it wasn't the case I think the system
would still be a success yeah absolutely
sounds like it but compatibility with
current operating systems probably
doesn't really exist there is no
compatibility whatsoever that's maybe a
good thing for a change I mean we have
to start at some point again well
there's there's I guess so we do have a
one form of compatibility which is if
you have c-sharp code so two CLR you can
run it on singular it's kind of like
porting between different versions of
UNIX if you're an eye-level you just run
the code you have mucked around
low-level it's not you know the the I
guess the compatibility really gets back
to the core idea this is a research
prototype you know my job as an
operating systems researching researcher
at Microsoft is to try out radical new
idea so far out in the futures I can see
which those ideas work the ones that
work I come back to the product types
and I say hey you should come try to put
incorporate these items into your
product and they can figure out how to
do compatibility and you know and then
the other thing is sometimes we produce
negative results in fact dandling our
former vice president used to say if we
don't fail half the time we're eating
grass absolutely so when we fail we go
the product guys and we say hey we tried
this really aggressive thing
it's not gonna give you the desired
results so don't go down this pathway so
is there any interest from the product
group is it going to be in Windows 2012
that's something well so the way we do
tech transfer most of the time a
Microsoft is we don't pick up say the
entire code base to say ok singularity
is going to be the next version or
window so what we do is we transfer idea
ideas yeah and there are already ideas
filtering out into the end of the
product groups and the seal our team and
into the windows team cool and you know
some of the ideas we'll get out there
sooner than and some of them will get
out laters but I have but we've I think
we've had we've had a much stronger
impact than I anticipated when we
started the project so to wrap this up
since we're talking about ideas and
concepts I think one other conclusion
from this project might also be that the
combination of a good architecture good
concepts a language that has those
concepts as first-class citizens and the
useful tools for it
for example analysis tools that these
three building blocks are probably a
very good set of ingredients for
building really good systems that's
exactly the message and of course I
didn't come up with that it's in the
paper but I mean I really like this
message and it's not limited to
operating systems yeah I I think it's
very true you know I think the ideas can
be applied in lots of places you know
one of the when we started the project
one of the key ideas was particularly
around the static analysis and the
verification tools and you know the the
tools people in the research and the
ticket and the product groups as well
have made tremendous progress over the
last decade and it's great to see those
tools getting applied No ok is there
anything else I should have asked or
some pearls of wisdom that you want to
leave with our listeners I've got no
wisdom whatsoever however I did want to
say one thing you know so we've been
talking here with me one person and you
know this is singularity was it was
actually a product of a large number of
people we had about 30 researchers and
Microsoft Research in build across both
our Redmond Lab in our Silicon Valley
and our Cambridge labs as well you know
just it's been a fantastic experience
just
working with some of these best
researchers in the entire world and I'm
just thrilled to death they let me work
with them as well absolutely so thank
you and all the others for sharing this
was out with us I think this was a real
for me was a really inspiring paper and
episode thank you thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the dick reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team @ SI radio net or if it's
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie Crowell
and the pot site Music Network for the
music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle